I'm a very lucky person.
أنا انسانة محظوظة جداً.
I've been privileged to see so much of our beautiful Earth
فقد حظيت برؤية أجزاء كبيرة من أرضنا الجميلة
and the people and creatures that live on it.
ورؤية الناس و المخلوقات التي تعيش عليها.
And my passion was inspired at the age of seven,
و قد أُثير شغفي في سن السابعة
when my parents first took me to Morocco,
عندما سافر بي والداي إلى المغرب لأول مرة
at the edge of the Sahara Desert.
على أطراف الصحراء الكبرى.
Now imagine a little Brit
تخيلوا الآن بريطانية صغيرة
somewhere that wasn't cold and damp like home.
في مكان لم يكن بارداً و رطباً كالوطن.
What an amazing experience.
يالها من تجربة رائعة.
And it made me want to explore more.
وقد جعلتني أرغب باكتشاف المزيد.
So as a filmmaker,
لذا و كمخرجة افلام،
I've been from one end of the Earth to the other
فقد كنت أجوب الأرض من أقاصيها إلى أقاصيها
trying to get the perfect shot
في محاولة للحصول على اللقطة المثالية
and to capture animal behavior never seen before.
والتقاط سلوك حيواني لم تسبق رؤيته من قبل.
And what's more, I'm really lucky,
وما هو أكثر من ذلك، أنا محظوظة حقاً،
because I get to share that with millions of people worldwide.
لأنني تمكنت من مشاركة ذلك مع ملايين الناس في جميع أنحاء العالم.
Now the idea of having new perspectives of our planet
الآن فكرة وجود آفاق جديدة لكوكبنا
and actually being able to get that message out
وكوني في الواقع قادرة على تبليغ هذه الرسالة
gets me out of bed every day with a spring in my step.
يجعلني أنهض من سريري كل يوم وكلّي سعادة و حماس.
You might think that it's quite hard
قد تعتقدون أنه من الصعب جداً
to find new stories and new subjects,
ايجاد أخبار ومواضيع جديدة،
but new technology is changing the way we can film.
ولكن التكنولوجيا الجديدة تغيّر الطريقة التي يمكننا من خلالها أن نصّور.
It's enabling us to get fresh, new images
فهي تمكننا من الحصول على صور نقية و غريبة
and tell brand new stories.
و من رواية قصص مميزة و جديدة.
In Nature's Great Events,
في "الأحداث الكبرى في الطبيعة"،
a series for the BBC that I did with David Attenborough,
و هي سلسلة للـ بي بي سي صنعتها مع ديفيد اتينبورو,
we wanted to do just that.
أردنا أن نقوم بذلك.
Images of grizzly bears are pretty familiar.
إنّ صور الدببة الرمادية مألوفة جداً.
You see them all the time, you think.
يمكنكم رؤيتها طوال الوقت، أو هكذا تظنون.
But there's a whole side to their lives that we hardly ever see
ولكن هناك جانب في حياتهم قلّما نراه
and had never been filmed.
ولم يتم تصويره أبداً.
So what we did, we went to Alaska,
لذلك ما قمنا به هو أننا ذهبنا إلى ألاسكا،
which is where the grizzlies rely
و فيها تأوي الدببة الرمادية
on really high, almost inaccessible, mountain slopes
إلى المنحدرات الجبلية العالية، التي قد يصعب الوصول ،
for their denning.
لحماية نفسها.
And the only way to film that is a shoot from the air.
والطريقة الوحيدة لتصوير ذلك هي أن يتم أخذ اللقطة من الجو.
(Video) David Attenborough: Throughout Alaska and British Columbia,
(فيديو) ديفيد اتينبورو: في أنحاء ألاسكا وكولومبيا البريطانية،
thousands of bear families are emerging from their winter sleep.
آلاف من أُسر الدببة تخرج من سباتها الشتوي.
There is nothing to eat up here,
لا يوجد شيء ليُؤكل هنا،
but the conditions were ideal for hibernation.
لكن الظروف كانت مثالية للسبات الشتوي.
Lots of snow in which to dig a den.
الكثير من الثلوج لحفر الوكر.
To find food, mothers must lead their cubs down to the coast,
من أجل البحث عن الغذاء، يجب أن تقود الأمهات دياسمها نزولاً إلى الساحل،
where the snow will already be melting.
حيث تكون الثلوج قد ذابت بالفعل.
But getting down can be a challenge for small cubs.
لكن النزول قد يشكل تحدياّ للدياسم الصغيرة.
These mountains are dangerous places,
تُعد هذه الجبال أماكن خطيرة،
but ultimately the fate of these bear families,
ولكنّها في نهاية المطاف هي قدر أسر الدببة هذه،
and indeed that of all bears around the North Pacific,
في الواقع, جميع الدببة التي تعيش حول المحيط الهادئ،
depends on the salmon.
تعتمد على السالمون.
KB: I love that shot.
أحب هذه اللقطة.
I always get goosebumps every time I see it.
و دائماً ارتعد خوفاً في كل مرة أراها.
That was filmed from a helicopter
لقد تم تصويرها من طائرة عامودية
using a gyro-stabilized camera.
باستخدام كاميرا مستقرة الدوران.
And it's a wonderful bit of gear,
وهي أداة رائعة،
because it's like having a flying tripod, crane and dolly all rolled into one.
لأنها مثل امتلاك حامل ثلاثي و رافعة و حامل بعجلات, جميعها مدمجة في أداة واحدة.
But technology alone isn't enough.
لكن التكنولوجيا لوحدها ليست كافية.
To really get the money shots,
للحصول فعلاّ على اللقطات المربحة،
it's down to being in the right place at the right time.
فهذا يستلزم التواجد في المكان المناسب في الوقت المناسب.
And that sequence was especially difficult.
و ذلك التسلسل كان صعباً للغاية.
The first year we got nothing.
في السنة الأولى لم نحصل على شيء.
We had to go back the following year,
كان علينا أن نعود في السنة التالية،
all the way back to the remote parts of Alaska.
من البداية إلى أن نصل للمناطق النائية في ألاسكا.
And we hung around with a helicopter for two whole weeks.
و قد حلّقنا بطائرة الهليكوبتر لمدة أسبوعين كاملين.
And eventually we got lucky.
وحالفنا الحظ في النهاية.
The cloud lifted, the wind was still,
انقشع السحاب، والرياح كانت ساكنة،
and even the bear showed up.
وحتى الدببة ظهرت.
And we managed to get that magic moment.
وتمكنا من التقاط تلك اللحظة الآسرة.
For a filmmaker,
بالنسبة لي كمخرجة أفلام،
new technology is an amazing tool,
تعتبر التكنولوجيا الحديثة أداة مذهلة،
but the other thing that really, really excites me
ولكن الشيء الآخر الذي يثيرني جداً جداً
is when new species are discovered.
هو عندما يتم اكتشاف الأنواع الجديدة.
Now, when I heard about one animal,
الآن، عندما سمعت عن حيوان واحد،
I knew we had to get it for my next series,
أدركت أنه يجب علينا الحصول عليه من أجل السلسلة القادمة،
Untamed Americas, for National Geographic.
"الأمريكيتين الجامحتين "، لناشيونال جيوغرافيك.
In 2005, a new species of bat was discovered
في عام 2005، تم اكتشاف نوع جديد من الخفافيش
in the cloud forests of Ecuador.
في غابات السحاب في الإكوادور.
And what was amazing about that discovery
وما كان مذهلاً حول هذا الاكتشاف
is that it also solved the mystery
هو أنه أيضا حل لغز
of what pollinated a unique flower.
تلقيح الزهرة الفريدة.
It depends solely on the bat.
إنها تعتمد فقط على الخفافيش.
Now, the series hasn't even aired yet,
و بما أن السلسلة لم تُبث حتى الآن,
so you're the very first to see this.
فإنكم ستكونون أول من يشاهد هذا.
See what you think.
انظروا ملياً.
(Video) Narrator: The tube-lipped nectar bat.
(فيديو) المعلق: خفاش الرحيق أنبوبي الشفتين.
A pool of delicious nectar
تجمّع للرحيق اللذيذ
lies at the bottom of each flower's long flute.
يقع في الجزء السفلي من المتاع الطويل لكل زهرة.
But how to reach it?
ولكن كيف يمكن الوصول إليه؟
Necessity is the mother of evolution.
الحاجة أم الإختراع.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
This two-and-a-half-inch bat
هذا الخفاش الذي يبلغ طوله بوصتين ونصف
has a three-and-a-half-inch tongue,
يمتلك لساناً طوله ثلاثة بوصات ونصف،
the longest relative to body length
وهو الأطول, نسبةً إلى طول الجسم,
of any mammal in the world.
من أي حيوان ثديي في العالم.
If human, he'd have a nine-foot tongue.
فإذا كان إنساناً، لبلغ طول لسانه تسع بوصات.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
KB: What a tongue.
يا له من لسان!
We filmed it by cutting a tiny little hole in the base of the flower
لقد قمنا بتصويره من خلال عمل فجوة صغيرة نسبياّ في قاعدة الزهرة
and using a camera that could slow the action by 40 times.
واستخدام كاميرا تستطيع إبطاء الحركة إلى أربعين مرة.
So imagine how quick that thing is in real life.
فتخيلوا كم سرعة هذا الشيء في الحياة الحقيقية.
Now people often ask me, "Where's your favorite place on the planet?"
كثيراً ما يسألني الناس، "ما هو مكانك المفضل على هذا الكوكب؟"
And the truth is I just don't have one.
وفي الواقع, ليس لدي مكان مفضل.
There are so many wonderful places.
هناك العديد من الأماكن الرائعة.
But some locations draw you back time and time again.
ولكن بعض الأماكن تجعلك تعود إليها مراراً و تكرارً.
And one remote location --
و هناك منطقة نائية --
I first went there as a backpacker;
ذهبت إليها أول مرة كرحالة؛
I've been back several times for filming,
ثم عدت إليها عدة مرات للتصوير،
most recently for Untamed Americas --
آخرُها لتصوير برنامج الأمريكتين الجامحتين --
it's the Altiplano in the high Andes of South America,
إنها ألتي بلانو في جبال الأنديز العالية "في أمريكا الجنوبية"،
and it's the most otherworldly place I know.
وهي أكثر منطقة ساحرة عرفتها.
But at 15,000 feet, it's tough.
ولكن على ارتفاع خمسة عشر ألف قدم، فإنها قاسية.
It's freezing cold,
إنها باردة و متجمدة،
and that thin air really gets you.
وذلك الهواء الرقيق يؤذيك بالفعل.
Sometimes it's hard to breathe,
في بعض الأحيان يكون التنفس صعب،
especially carrying all the heavy filming equipment.
خاصة عند حمل جميع معدات التصوير الثقيلة.
And that pounding head just feels like a constant hangover.
مع تلك الدقات في الرأس وكأنك تعاني من دوار مستمر.
But the advantage of that wonderful thin atmosphere
لكن الفائدة من هذا الجو الرقيق الرائع
is that it enables you to see the stars in the heavens
هو أنه يمكنك من رؤية النجوم في السماء
with amazing clarity.
بوضوح رائع.
Have a look.
القوا نظرة.
(Video) Narrator: Some 1,500 miles south of the tropics,
(فيديو) معلق: في مكان ما على بعد ألف و خمسمائة ميل إلى الجنوب من المناطق المدارية،
between Chile and Bolivia,
بين تشيلي وبوليفيا،
the Andes completely change.
تتغير جبال الأنديز تماماً.
It's called the Altiplano, or "high plains" --
إنها منطقة تدعى بـ ألتي بلانو، أو "السهول العالية"-
a place of extremes
إنها منطقة متطرفة
and extreme contrasts.
مليئة بالتناقضات الشديدة.
Where deserts freeze
حيث تتجمد فيها الصحاري
and waters boil.
وتغلي المياه.
More like Mars than Earth,
تشبه في ذلك كوكب المريخ أكثر من كوكب الأرض،
it seems just as hostile to life.
تبدو كما لو أنها معادية للحياة.
The stars themselves --
النجوم نفسها -
at 12,000 feet, the dry, thin air
الإرتفاع البالغ اثني عشر قدماً، الجفاف، الهواء الرقيق
makes for perfect stargazing.
يجعل المكان مثالياً لمشاهدة النجوم .
Some of the world's astronomers have telescopes nearby.
بعض علماء الفلك في العالم يعملون و مناظيرهم بالقرب منهم.
But just looking up with the naked eye,
لكن مجرد النظر بالعين المجردة،
you really don't need one.
يغنيك عنها.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
KB: Thank you so much
شكرا جزيلاً لكم
for letting me share some images
لأنكم سمحتم لي أن أشارككم بعض الصور
of our magnificent, wonderful Earth.
من أرضنا الخلابة و الرائعة.
Thank you for letting me share that with you.
شكرا لكم لأنكم سمحتم لي أن أشارككم هذا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)